<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Long lookt for is come at last People were fill'd with discontent, wanting their wisht for Parliament: but call'd by Charles our gracious King, merrily now they laugh and sing. To the tune of, Let bumpers go round, &amp;c. Papists shall here receive their fatal doom, because they've acted for the Pope of Rome.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 6KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 1 1-bit group-IV TIFF page image.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B26201</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99827810</idno>
  <idno type="VID">198006</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240885705</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing L2989</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99827810</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-99827810e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B26201)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 198006)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 21232:78-79)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Long lookt for is come at last People were fill'd with discontent, wanting their wisht for Parliament: but call'd by Charles our gracious King, merrily now they laugh and sing. To the tune of, Let bumpers go round, &amp;c. Papists shall here receive their fatal doom, because they've acted for the Pope of Rome.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>1 sheet ([1] p.) : ill.  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for F. Coles, T. Vere, J. Wright, J. Clark, W.T. and T.P.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1680?]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Verse - "Now the Parliament sits, traytors look to your hits,".</note>
                  <note>Place of publication from and date conjectured by Wing.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="corporate_name">England and Wales. --  Parliament --  Poetry --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Ballads, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-05 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-09 </date>
            <label>Kate Allen </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-09 </date>
            <label>Kate Allen</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="song">
            <pb facs="tcp:198006:1"/>
            <head>Long lookt for is come at last.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <l>People were fill'd with Discontent,</l>
                  <l>Wanting their wisht for Parliament:</l>
                  <l>But call'd by <hi>Charles</hi> our Gracious King,</l>
                  <l>Merrily now they Laugh and Sing.</l>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <opener>To the Tune of, <hi>Let Bumpers go round, &amp;c.</hi>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <head>
                     <l>Papists <hi>shall here receive their fatal Doom,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Because they've acted for the</hi> Pope <hi>of</hi> Rome.</l>
                  </head>
                  <figDesc>a man on a throne</figDesc>
               </figure>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>figures standing under an archway guarding a captive while armed men march past</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <lg>
               <l>NOw the Parliament Sits, Traytors look to your Hits,</l>
               <l>there's no doubt but they'l call you to Question,</l>
               <l>Some do boldly declare, that in Earnest you were,</l>
               <l>and I hope they will not go in Iest on:</l>
               <l>Th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n come to the Bar, since Invited you are,</l>
               <l>and freely acknowledge your Plots;</l>
               <l>For your great Friend the Pope, is almost out of Hope,</l>
               <l>and in each of your Scutcheons there's Damnable Blots:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Give Traytors their Due,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Give Traytors their Due,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>or else we shall find Loyal hearts but a few;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>For it is a sad thing,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>To Murther a King,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>and Destroy, and Destroy Religion too.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The Great Gun-powder-Plot, will ne'r be forgot,</l>
               <l>nor the Cruelties Papists intended,</l>
               <l>And no Man can tell, what would us have befell,</l>
               <l>if the Heavens had not us befriended:</l>
               <l>While for Mercy we pray'd, it was not Delay'd,</l>
               <l>but we found to our comfort and Ioy,</l>
               <l>That God would us keep, both Awake and Asleep,</l>
               <l>and the Pope and his Agents could not us Destroy:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Give Traytors their Due,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Give Traytors their Due,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>or else we shall find Loyal hearts but a few,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>For it is a sad thing,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>To Murder a King,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>and destroy, and destroy Religion too.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Since the Parliament then, is made up of brave men,</l>
               <l>and none Sits but are bravely esteemed;</l>
               <l>Let us Laugh and Rejoyce, at this Noble brave Choice,</l>
               <l>and thank God we from Foes are Redeemed:</l>
               <l>Live long then great <hi>Charles,</hi> with your Lords and your Earls</l>
               <l>who our Religion do strive to Defend,</l>
               <l>When the Pope doth come in, will our Sorrows begin,</l>
               <l>and there's no Man can tell when our Torments shall end:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Give Traytors their Due,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Give Traytors their Due, &amp;c.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:198006:1"/>
               <l>Then Blow merry Gales, for to fill up the Sails,</l>
               <l>and Transport all our Foes from the Nation;</l>
               <l>For they Comfort will find, that are all of one mind,</l>
               <l>and Division's the Devils Creation:</l>
               <l>Sure he's not very Wise, who doth Shapes Idolize,</l>
               <l>or suppose that the Pope can Forgive;</l>
               <l>For he is but a Man, and pray tell me how than,</l>
               <l>can he the Sin-loaded poor Sinner Relieve?</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Give Traytors their Due,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Give Traytors their Due, &amp;c.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But since at the worst, we by them are Accurst,</l>
               <l>and all Hereticks we are supposed;</l>
               <l>Were it well understood, they do thirst after Blood,</l>
               <l>our Creator he certainly knows it:</l>
               <l>What Devices they had for to make their Hearts glad,</l>
               <l>they did Surfeit with hopes to Destroy,</l>
               <l>This Plot we do know, was laid long ago,</l>
               <l>but the Heavens did Smile, and now fills us with joy:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Give Traytors their Due,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Give Traytors their Due, &amp;c.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Long lookt for at last, to the Plot gives a Blast,</l>
               <l>and the Parliament now doth befriend us,</l>
               <l>And doth seperate those, whom we lookt on as Foes,</l>
               <l>what Misery then can attend us:</l>
               <l>Let us pray Night and Day, since God found out a way,</l>
               <l>to Deliver us from Sword and Fire;</l>
               <l>And we are not Bereft, but have Witnesses left,</l>
               <l>to Attest what the Papists did freely <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eare:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Give Traytors their due,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Give Traytors their due, &amp;c.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But this proves a great Cross, and the Papists sad Loss,</l>
               <l>thus strangely to be Disappointed,</l>
               <l>When they thought they were sure, to bring us to their Lure,</l>
               <l>their whole Frame it was strangely Disjoynted:</l>
               <l>And their Friends (as they thought) have our Happiness wrought,</l>
               <l>then give the Almighty the Praise,</l>
               <l>Who takes no Delight, in such Deeds of Dark Night,</l>
               <l>but Discovery's made us by several ways:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Give Traytors their due,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Give Traytors their due, &amp;c.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And now for to Close, let us pray for our Foes,</l>
               <l>that God wou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d be pleas'd to Indue them</l>
               <l>With a sight of their Sins, since all <hi>Europe</hi> begins</l>
               <l>with a Circumspect Eye for to view them:</l>
               <l>Oh, let them Repent, for their Wicked Intent</l>
               <l>was the Innocent Blood for to spiil;</l>
               <l>But our Great God above, who's the Author of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ove,</l>
               <l>declares 'tis against his most Heavenly Wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Give Traytors their due,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Give Traytors their due, &amp;c.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>
               <hi>Printed for</hi> F. C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>s, T. Vere, J. Wright, J. Cla<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>, W. T. <hi>and</hi> T. P.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>